<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and faithful narrative of the much to be lamented death of Mr. William Tyrrell and the more to be magnified preservation of Sr. John Rous of Henham, Baronet, and divers other gentlemen ... published for the vindication of Gods truth and those persons honour and credit, from some foul and scandalous aspersions cast upon them in alying libell entituled, Sad and lamentable news from Suffolk / by Lionel Gatford ...</title>
            <author>Gatford, Lionel, d. 1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12255593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12255593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57406</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57406)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 185:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and faithful narrative of the much to be lamented death of Mr. William Tyrrell and the more to be magnified preservation of Sr. John Rous of Henham, Baronet, and divers other gentlemen ... published for the vindication of Gods truth and those persons honour and credit, from some foul and scandalous aspersions cast upon them in alying libell entituled, Sad and lamentable news from Suffolk / by Lionel Gatford ...</title>
                  <author>Gatford, Lionel, d. 1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iames Lawson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tyrrell, William.</term>
               <term>Rous, John, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Sad and lamentable newes from Suffolk.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57406:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57406:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true and faithfull NARRATIVE Of the much to be lamented death of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> WILLIAM TYRRELL And the more to be magnified preſervation of Sr. JOHN ROUS Of <hi>Henham</hi> Baronet, And divers other Gentlemen of worth, and perſons well reputed in their Country.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED For the vindication of Gods Truth, and thoſe Perſons honour and credit, from ſome foul and ſcandalous aſperſions caſt upon them, in a lying Libell Entituled, <hi>Sad and Lamentable Newes from</hi> Suffolk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By LIONELL G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>TFORD <hi>D. D.</hi> and Rector of <hi>Dinnington</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes Lawſon,</hi> and ſold at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57406:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57406:2"/>
            <head>A true and faithfull NARRATIVE OF The much to be lamented death of Mr. <hi>VVilliam Tyrrell,</hi> and the more to be magnified preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Sir <hi>John Rous</hi> of <hi>Henham</hi> Baronet, and divers other Gentlemen of worth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>ou have heard not long ſince, both by Books and Ballads, (whether from the ſame or ſeverall hands, is ſomewhat doubtfull, though the Title and Relations be the ſame, ſo far as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates in iniquity thought fit to lay their lies and ſlanders together) <hi>Sad and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Newes from</hi> Suffolk, being (as they falſly term it) <hi>A true and perfect Relation of the great Thunderclaps, and Lightning, that fell upon the Houſe of</hi> Mr. Abſalon <hi>at Wangford, where</hi> Mr. Torrill, Mr. Brome (for ſo they call them) Mr. Blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, Mr. Lemon, <hi>and divers other Gentlemen were drinking Healths. And the manner how the ſaid Thunderclaps,</hi> &amp;c. as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in their ſwelling Titles. <hi>And all this</hi> (ſay they) <hi>atteſted by the fore-man of the Jury,</hi> Mr. John Gibſon, <hi>who was ſummoned upon the Crowners Queſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that God may be glorified in his wonderfull works, both of mercy and judgement, his Truth magnified, the Honours and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Names, both of the mercifully preſerved and miraculouſly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57406:3"/>
hurt Gentlemen vindicated, and loud Lies, ſlanders and reproaches, of the Saint-ſeeming, Devil-imitating, and Hell-breathing Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, that have divulged and publiſhed thoſe pernicious and peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous reports to the world, be thrown back into their own impudent faces: I ſhall firſt give you a true Narrative of that whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as I received it from the Pen of a Perſon of Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, who, I verily believe, abhorres to tell an untruth, or ſpeak deceitfully <hi>for God</hi> himſelf, as <hi>Job</hi>'s expreſſion is, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. much more for the ſalving of any mans credit: and that done, I ſhall give you ſome few animadverſions thereon, and ſo leave the Libellers to repent of their lies and ſlanders, or to ſuffer for them, as God and the Executioners of his wrath ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the laſt of <hi>July</hi> after Dinner, Sir <hi>John Rous</hi> of <hi>Henham</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> a Gentleman of known honour and honeſty, and highly beloved and eſteemed in his Country, and a member of this preſent Parliament took out with him Mr. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Tyrrell,</hi> that was (if I miſtake not) a Kinſman of his, and well reſpected of him, to walk with him into ſome Grounds of his, not far from his houſe; where they met with Mr. <hi>Thomas Abſalon</hi> of <hi>Wangford,</hi> that hired ſome Grounds of Sir <hi>John;</hi> and he entreated Sir <hi>John</hi> to goe to his houſe, and the rather, for that Captain <hi>Lemon,</hi> and his Nephew Mr. <hi>John Lemon</hi> were there, and the latter of them had a deſire to ſpeak with him, being to goe the next day towards <hi>London.</hi> Sir <hi>John Rous</hi> promiſed to call there, ere he returned home; and as he was going, he found Mr. <hi>Breame,</hi> and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mr. <hi>James Breame</hi> ſelling of Cattell to a <hi>Butcher,</hi> and called to them; and they, together with Mr. <hi>Blowgate,</hi> Sir <hi>John</hi>'s Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and <hi>Robert Brown</hi> another of his Servants (who had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with his Gun, as he uſed frequently to doe) went along with him. And when all, or the moſt part of theſe Perſons had been in the <hi>Parlour</hi> of Mr. <hi>Abſalons</hi> houſe ſome ſmall time, <hi>viz.</hi> about half an hour, or not ſo much, and had onely received the civility of a Cup or two of <hi>Beer</hi> (there being nothing, no not ſo much as the <hi>Beer</hi> provided on purpoſe for them, nor the leaſt deſign of any ſuch meeting pre-determined many minutes before) on a ſudden there happened a very great ſhower of Rain, and after the violence of that was a little over, there followed a clap of thunder, which break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt over the ſaid houſe, ſeemed much greater to them and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57406:3"/>
neighbours adjoyning, then it did to thoſe that were ſome ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from thence, it being not taken notice of at all, by thoſe that were within leſſe then a mile of that houſe. And ſome people that were in the Yards belonging to that houſe, and to the houſes near it, ſaw (as they affirm) a Ball of Fire fall upon the houſe, which raiſed and brake ſome of the Tyles, ſhivered a Sparre in the Garret into fourty ſhivers, rent ſome of the Studds of the houſe, brake thorow, or otherwiſe found its paſſage into the Chamber over the Parlour, and there tore the Bed-poſts and back of the Bed into many pieces; and fell into a hole of the boards, and brake thorow the Seeling into the Parlour, where the Gentlemen were; Sir <hi>John Rous</hi> ſitting at the end of the Table, and Mr. <hi>Tyrrell</hi> by him at the ſide thereof, with the Window juſt behind him, and Mr. <hi>Breame</hi> and his Brother by Mr. <hi>Tyrrell,</hi> Captain <hi>Lemon</hi> at the other end of the Table, and Mr. <hi>Blowgate</hi> at ſome diſtance from them. And the ſulphurious Vapour (like tearing Granado) or rather as much tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending it, as Nature does Art, or the more immediate work of the God of Nature, does the work of Man) diſperſed it ſelf in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, without any fire or flaſh of Lightning ſeen by any of the company; and in an inſtant ſtruck Mr. <hi>Tyrrell</hi> dead as he ſate, beat down one of the <hi>Breames</hi> upon the floor, and threw the other upon the Table, lifted Mr. <hi>Blowgate</hi> out of his Chayre, and caſt him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſide of the Table, but did not carry him out of the Parlour to the top of the Room, and then caſt him upon a Table (as the non-ſenſicall Pamphleteer aſſerts in the Title of his Libell) and him Captain <hi>Lemon</hi> help't into his Chayre again, though he was not at that time ſenſible of that kindneſſe; Mr. <hi>John Lemon</hi> was ſtruck down flat upon his back as he was coming into the houſe, &amp; taken up dead, but being preſently carried into the open aire, he ſoon revived, and was ſo well, as that, according to his intention, he began his Journey toward <hi>London</hi> the next day, but Mr. <hi>William Tyrrell</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recovered. The Woman of the houſe, being in the next Room with her Children, ſaw (as ſhe ſaith) a flaſh of fire glide thorow the Room, and ſhoot out at the Door, which ſhe thought would have done much miſchief in that Room alſo, had not the Door been open. And it is ſaid by others that were abroad, that they ſaw ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flaſh of five flye out at that Window, againſt which Mr. <hi>Tyrrell</hi> ſate: in the Chamber there was found a corner of a Window ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57406:4"/>
diſplaced, as if it had been forced out with ſome difficultie, and the end thereof, as if it had been black't with a Candle: And there was all that Evening, a very ſtrong ſmell of fire and ſulphur in the houſe. But bleſſed for ever be that Almighty and moſt mercifull God, that is <hi>ſlow to anger, and plenteous in mercy;</hi> yea, that <hi>in his wrath remembers mercy,</hi> Sir <hi>John Rous,</hi> the principall man aimed at by the Phanatick Libellers, and ſome of his company, and divers in the ſame houſe, had not, that I can hear either from their friends or enemies, the leaſt harm; but were as miraculouſly preſerved, as one was ſtrangely ſlain, and others more gently ſmitten. And this is the full and clear truth of the buſineſſe, ſo far as could be collected from perſons ſo aſtoniſhed and amazed, as thoſe were that were moſt concerned; and from the teſtimonies of ſuch ſober and diſcreet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as were either ſad ſpectatours of it, or ſerious enquirers into it.</p>
            <p>And though this bare Narrative be a ſufficient diſcovery of the malicious Lies and Slanders of the Libellers, yet ſeeing they have not onely publiſhed their malicious Lies and Slanders in Print, but have Commented thereon with as much artifice, as that darkneſſe, which they call <hi>the Light within them,</hi> would give them leave to uſe. I hope it will not be thought unworthy of my Profeſſion, or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming that ſervice and gratitude, wherein I ſtand obliged to Sir <hi>John Rous,</hi> to make ſome animadverſions upon the whole matter, as they have repreſented it, and to give Sir <hi>John,</hi> and his Friends and Servants, which were either untouch't by thoſe fiery Darts of God, that ſo ſtrangely flew up and down amongſt them, or were but gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſmitten by them, ſome becoming adviſe for their making good uſe of that their miraculous deliverance.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, take notice that he that atteſts the matter of the Libell, is aſhamed of his own name, <hi>Daniel Ewin;</hi> and therefore he borrows the name of <hi>John Gibſon</hi> to ſubſcribe it. And indeed he might well be aſhamed to ſet his own name to it, he having been ſuch a known Lyar, ſo notorious in that ſervice of his Maſter the Devill, and ſuch a plunderer of the Goods, ſuch a pillager of the Eſtates, ſuch a depraver of the Names, and ſuch a perſecutor of the Perſons of all faithfull and loyall ſubjects, that his hands or tongue could reach; that had the name of <hi>Daniel Ewin</hi> been ſet to it, all that know him would have ſuſpected that litle truth which he relates, becauſe ſo lewd a Lyar related it: and his many lies intermixed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57406:4"/>
with it would have been immediately thrown in his face by all his neighbours about him, with ſuch deteſtation and abhorrencie, as that he muſt have fled his Countrey ſooner then he intends (though it is believed that his place of aboad will ſpue him out very ſuddenly) or elſe have indured a ſtorm, as hard to be indured by him, as that which the perſecuted Perſons, through Gods unſpeakable mercy to them, were inabled to endure.</p>
            <p>In the next place, give me leave to inform you of the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent malice of this <hi>Daniel Ewin,</hi> who becauſe Sr. <hi>John Rous,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his duty incumbent on him, as one of the chief Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners in the <hi>Militia,</hi> and now one of his Majeſties Deputy Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> had curbed the daring inſolencies of the ſaid <hi>Ewin</hi> and ſome of his fellow-Phanaticks, and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuppreſſed ſome of their rebellious deſignes, he took now this opportunity to beſpatter, as much as he could, Sr. <hi>John's</hi> unſpotted name, as being no other way able to aſperſe him. And being made fore-man of the <hi>Coroners inqueſt,</hi> he laboured according to his little wit and ſuperabundant Villanie, (wherein he had been a long time practiſed) to have made the death of Mr <hi>Tyrrell,</hi> murder: and when he found that to be too groſs and ridiculous even in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the meaneſt Juror, (though to the ſhame of thoſe that are intruſted with impannelling of Juries, they that ſerve upon Juries of life and death, are too often none of the wiſeſt of the Countrey) he then thought that the ſuggeſtion of intended drunkenneſs or exceſſive drinking, would be the moſt eaſily inſinuated into thoſe of his own fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, &amp; ſtick faſteſt upon thoſe of the Royal party, amongſt whom Sr. <hi>John Rous</hi> was a Gentleman of no little eminencie. Wherefore he adds in his information, that Sr. <hi>John Row,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Torrill,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Brome</hi> (as he miſcalls them; for either he could not ſpell their names aright, or elſe his brother Phanatick, that compoſed his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell for him, had not the true key or character of his lying letters) and his brother, Mr. <hi>Lemon</hi> and his brother, Mr. <hi>Blowgate</hi> and Mr. <hi>Robert Brown</hi> ſervants to the ſaid Sr. <hi>John Row,</hi> with divers other Gentlemen, (that were there inviſibly, for he had named the whole company, only he thought there yet wanted ſome more to make what followes the more probable) met on purpoſe to drink out a Barrell of March beer; the Kennel-defiling Rythmer ſcores it up a Pipe of Beer. Whereas, neither was there any meeting at all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57406:5"/>
aſſigned many minutes before, (as was before declared by thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen but they met all accidentally, neither did they, when they met, meet with any ſuch proviſion as a Barrel of March Beer or a Pipe of other Beer, but the Gentleman that gave them that litle drink which they drank, did in probable civility give them the beſt that he had, whether it were Beer or Ale, of March or any other moneth; and they in good manners did not inquire into the age of it, as it ſeems the fore-man of the <hi>Coroners Inquest</hi> thought fit to doe, or rather adventured to report it, to make way for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of inflaming and intoxicating. Only I wonder that <hi>Ewin,</hi> the Brewer or Brewſter of that Lye of March Beer, ſhould ſo much forget the anagramme of his own name, as not rather to have told us of ſo much wine that was ſent in before hand from <hi>Blithborough,</hi> from whence he borrowed the name of <hi>John Gibſon,</hi> or that his <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew-faire Ballad-maker</hi> ſhould ſo miſtake, as to call a pipe of <hi>Tobacco</hi> a pipe of <hi>Beer;</hi> But let ſuch Lyars beware that when they have thus aſperſed ſober and worthy perſons with drinking of what and as much liquor as they pleaſe, their own tongues ſet on fire of hell (as St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeakes) doe not one day, when it will be too late, cry out, for a drop of cold water to cool them.</p>
            <p>Take one thing more from the Fore-man of the Jury his atteſted relation. He tells us, that the force of the thunder came in at the window againſt which Mr. <hi>Torrill</hi> was ſitting; and yet ſome very few lines before he ſaith (and it is in a manner the only truth in his relation) that the force of the thunder-clap fell upon the tyles of the houſe and broke into the Parlour chamber and from thence fell down into the Parlour where the Gentlemen were ſitting. A Lyar, you ſee, had need to have a better memory then the fore-man in this Lye, had: and he ſaith he was both an eare and eye witneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, which I confeſſe I doe not underſtand how it was poſſible; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he ſaw the Thunder that came in at the Parlour Window, and heard the Thunderclap that fell upon the Tyles, and ſo thorow the Parlour Chamber into the Parlour: and indeed we men of carnall Eyes and Eares doe not know (as they often tell us) what ſuch ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Eyes and Eares, as <hi>Ewin</hi> and ſuch Phanaticks have, can ſee and hear. But this I am ſure, <hi>Ewin</hi> did at this time very much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee what he was ſummoned to view and obſerve; and is one, that conſtanly hears as ill, as any man in that County: and both he and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57406:5"/>
his Pamphleter deſerve to looſe their eyes and ears too for abuſing ſo many thouſand eyes and ears as they have done with their Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Lyes in print, which mindes me of ſpeaking ſomething to their Hypocriſie as well as to their Lying.</p>
            <p>That prediction or propheſie of the ſpirit of God. 1 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4. v. 2. <hi>That in the latter times ſome ſhould depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devills, ſpeaking Lyes in hypocriſie, having their conſcience ſeared with an hot iron;</hi> is not more truly and exactly fulfilled in any, then in the Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of theſe times. and the hypocriticall Canting of thoſe Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, which I am preſenting to you, will witneſſe as much.</p>
            <p>The greateſt thing (ſaith the Libeller) that we can deſire (next to the glory of God) is our own ſalvation; and the ſweeteſt thing we can deſire, is the aſſurance of our ſalvation. And in this life we cannot get higher, then to be aſſured of that which in the next is to be enjoyed. Theſe are the charming termes, with which the compoſer of the Libell would lull you a ſleep, whil'ſt he poyſons your faith with a moſt venomous and falſe ſuggeſtion of the fore-named Gentlemans exceſſe in drinking at their meeting. Oh the matchleſſe boldneſſe of phanaticall impudence! could nothing, but the lifting men up with the thoughts of ſalvation and the aſſurance thereof, be thought on as a deluſion ſtrong enough to perſwade them to believe a lye? Certainly where ſalvation is but hoped for by any, all Lying, and eſpecially the belying and ſlandering of others, is abhorred and deteſted: for as all lying lips are an abomination to the Lord <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> 12.22. <hi>So he that ſpeakes lies in the name of the Lord, is ſo abominable unto men as well as to the Lord, that his own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother that begat him, ſhall ſay unto him, thou ſhalt not live, Zack.</hi> 13.3. And if <hi>whoſoever loveth and maketh a Lye ſhall not be ſuffered to enter into the gates of the heavenly Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem Revelat.</hi> 22. v. 15 and chap. 21. 27. much leſſe ſhall they be admitted to enter, that not only make lies, but make uſe of the talking of Gods glory and the aſſurance of mans ſalvation, to make way for their Lyes to enter the more ſmoothly and undeſcernably into mens hearts. Exceſſe of drinking is exceeding ſinfull; and, praiſed be God, there are many, very many, of the Kings faithfull and loyall ſubjects, that hate it in reallity, as much as any of your Phanatick crew doe in pretence. But withall we acknowledge, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57406:6"/>
we think it far worſe to be drunke with malice and envy, with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and rebellion, with violence and bloud, with oppreſſion and ſacriledge, with diſſimulation and hypocriſie, with errour and hereſie, then with <hi>wine</hi> or <hi>beer,</hi> or any other liquor. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ye would be ſaints indeed, as well as ſo reputed, let drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and other fowle ſcandalous ſinnes be abhorred of you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſinnes, and abhorred by God, and then you will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor lying and diſſembling as well as the reſt; and doe not think your ſelves, or rather call your ſelves Saints, (for ſurely ye cannot ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly think your ſelves ſo) becauſe ye abſtain from thoſe ſins from which the Devills themſelves abſtain, and in the mean time delight in thoſe, in which they moſt delight, and particularly in that ſinne of falſly accuſing your brethren, from which the Devill hath his name Diabolus, Devill, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 12. v. 10.</p>
            <p>But to trace this Libeller a little further. He tells us of two hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and that ſome ſaints enjoy a heaven while they are here on earth: and that all may enjoy two heavens, is (as he ſaith) the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his diſcourſe, and that this project may be publiſhed, he would lay down ſome cautionary motions for preventing exceſſe in drinking; conſidering the late, ſad and heavy judgements that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell divers Gentlemen in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> as they were drinking of healths &amp;c. O rare projectour that hath found out two heavens, and that the Saints enjoy one of thoſe heavens here on earth: I confeſſe the Scriptures make mention of three heavens the firſt the aereall hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which is the next above the earth: and from whence the birds and fowles; that fly therein are called the birds and fowles of heaven, and the clouds, the clouds of heaven; the ſecond the ſtarry heaven, under which name is comprehended not only the orbes of the planets, but that orbe alſo where the fixed ſtarres are and ſo all the whole extant from above the clouds, to that which is the place provided by Chriſt for the bleſſed for ever to remain in, and from it the Starres are called the Starres of heaven &amp;c. And then the third heaven, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. and is that heaven, into which Chriſt is according to his body aſcended, and of which he ſaith, that the Angells doe alwayes behold the face of my father which is in heaven; and he taught us to ſay. <hi>Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven.</hi> But all theſe three heavens are above the earth; only our earthly Dreamer (as S. <hi>Jude</hi> calls ſuch) hath dreamt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57406:6"/>
of another heaven upon earth, which ſome whom he calls Saints doe enjoy: whereas thoſe that are true reall Saints indeed, doe here on earth finde rather an hell then a heaven, by the reaſon of the many temptations and perſecutions, the miſeries and afflictions, the fightings without and the fears within, the wreſtlings and other incounters, that they of all men are daily either oppreſſed with or exerciſed by: inſomuch that if they had only hope in this life in Chriſt, they were of all men the moſt miſerable, But it is well for ſuch Saints as the Libeller and his fellow-brethren, that he hath found out for himſelf and them an heaven on earth; for now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, he and they, that have their portion in this life, may intitle themſelves to that newfound heaven: for as for heaven above; if all his lying Pamphlets were made into a paper Kite (which the boys about the city, as well as they love ſuch toyes will ſcarce take the pains to doe, knowing a more proper uſe for them, by throwing them down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) yet they would not mount him or his name, above the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of a pillory, and for his poor ſoul God be mercifull to him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he doe in time repent of his lying and ſlandering, of his hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and counterfeited ſanctity, it will need no other filth to clog its wings from ever ſoaring neerer the higheſt heaven, then that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where the Prince of the aire is ſometimes permitted to revell in; and ſuch projectors as he, may for a time be allowed to breath in.</p>
            <p>But who told him that the Gentlemen, met at <hi>Wangford</hi> were drinking of healths, &amp; that in exceſſe, when the late ſad &amp; heavy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments befell them? There is no mention of drinking healths, or drinking in exceſſe, in all the relation atteſted by <hi>Gibſon</hi> alias <hi>Ewin:</hi> but that they met to drink out a barrell of March Beer; which was alſo a loud one, as hath been allready ſhewn, but ſuppoſe they were drinking of healths, or did otherwiſe drink in exceſſe, (which is the meer fiction of the Libellers own Phanatick brain and that whereby he carryes away the whetſtone from <hi>Ewin</hi> himſelf) how dares the Libeller be ſo bold with with God and his judgements, which are ſo unſearchable as well as terrible, as to apply Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to any perſons whatſoever, ſo as to ſay, or ſuggeſt by way of intimation, that for this or that cauſe, God ſent ſuch or ſuch judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon ſuch and ſuch perſons; unleſſe God did, by thoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon thoſe perſons, indigitate thoſe cauſes ſo evidently, as that their ſinne might be viſibly read in the marks and characters of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57406:7"/>
thoſe judgements. And then too, men ought to be very wary and tender of judgeing others, leſt God himſelf, who is the Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all men, Judge them alſo for uſurping his Throne, and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Prerogative, by Judging of any of his: eſpecially ſo as to think them the greateſt ſinners, on whom God layes the ſoreſt judgements, when he ſpares others. Remember thoſe <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe blood <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their ſacrifices: and <hi>thoſe eighteen upon whom the Tower of Siloe fell and ſlew them,</hi> Luke 13. Chriſt himſelf aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures you, that <hi>they were not ſinners above all the Galileans,</hi> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that eſcaped thoſe judgments: but the prime uſe to be made by thoſe that eſcape Gods judgments, when others ſuffer under them or periſh by them, is (as our Saviour there intimates) <hi>to repent of their own ſins, leſt they alſo periſh.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſo much did God magnifie his mercy at that very time, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſo many alive, and ſome of them untoucht, when he took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way onely one of their company, and ſmote ſome of the reſt with ſo gentle a ſtroke, that their very preſervation rather ſpeaks their freeneſſe at that preſent from any ſuch foul crime, as the Libeller would fain faſten upon them, than give any juſt occaſion to any to ſuſpect them guilty thereof.</p>
            <p>But the Libeller goes on, <hi>You muſt, you'l ſay drink the Kings health;</hi> and to ſhew his Logick as well as his Rhetorick, he refutes the doing ſo, thus: <hi>Is it congruous in cups of exceſſe to drink the Kings health, when he preſerves his health by little drinking?</hi> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the man thinks, that they who drink the Kings health, doe not onely wiſh or pray for his health, or otherwiſe honourably ſpeak of him; but they mingle his health in their Cups, as they doe Sugar, or ſome other ingredients: or elſe what congruity is there in that pretty knacking ſaying of his? But who (I beſeech him) are they, that ſay, they muſt drink the Kings health? did thoſe Gentlemen ſay ſo? The Fore-man himſelf affirms no ſuch thing: and if they did drink his Majeſties health, might they not doe it without drinking it in Cups of exceſſe, and ſo preſerve their own health as well as drink his? It is beyond the limits of my vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to determine the lawfulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe of drinking the Kings health; for the Libeller quarrells onely at the drinking of it in Cups of exceſſe, and ſo far all ſober men concurre with him: but it may well be ſuſpected, that if he loved the King or his health ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57406:7"/>
well as he ſhould, he would not have crowded that paſſage into his Pamphlet ſo incongruouſly &amp; impertinently: but calumny knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of congruity or pertinency. The thing that he aimes at, is queſtionleſſe this, To have the world believe that ſuch a ſad and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable judgement fell ſuch a time, upon ſuch and ſuch Gentlemen for drinking of the Kings health. And whether this does not ſmell ſtrongly of the Phanatick humour, let himſelf judge; though I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Phanaticks will not thank him for one obſervation of his a little before, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Wine or Beer in a drunken exceſſe, inflames the heart, intoxicates the brain, and turns all Phanaticks:</hi> But tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I thank him for that ſaying; for, by this I conjecture, how he himſelf became ſo inflamed as he is, &amp; his brain crows ſo much as it does, and ſo he is turned all Phanatick; the poor man had taken a cup or two of exceſſe. Alas poor heart &amp; weak brain, beware how you meddle any more either with drinking or ſcribling a little too much: for you then throw about your Inke, you care not how, nor upon whom, but beſpatter thoſe whom either you know, or at leaſt dare not let them know your Name.</p>
            <p>He gives you a caution alſo againſt Oathes and Execrations; which he forceth into his Libell by head and ſhoulders, and all to throw more dirt into thoſe faces, which either he never ſaw, or knows them to be ſuch, that the leaſt ſpot cannot ſtick upon them, eſpecially them that he chiefly aimed at.</p>
            <p>At the laſt he whines out ſomething that might from another mouth, be thought to ſavour of Loyaltie; and therefore as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, when he heard a very bad man ſpeak a very good ſentence, entreated an honeſt man that ſtood by, to ſpeak that ſentence over again, for that it would ſound much better out of a better mouth: So I could wiſh, that thoſe good words, which this wicked Libeller hath let fall concerning our Gracious and Dread Soveraign, and the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and devotion, with which his good Subjects ſhould as good Chriſtians rejoyce, for his return and reeſtabliſhment amongſt us (which I underſtand by that expreſſion of his, <hi>Let us all heighten the joyful ſhout of a King amongſt us</hi>) I could wiſh, I ſay, that ſome honeſt &amp; cordial Loyaliſt had uttered thoſe words, &amp; they would have ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much ſweeter, and not ſo hollow &amp; crack't as they doe. But Saint <hi>James</hi> hath much abated the wonder of an evill tongue ſpeaking ſometimes good words; when he ſaith, <hi>James</hi> 3. <hi>Therewith bleſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57406:8"/>
we God even the Father, and therewith curſe we men, which are made after the ſimilitude of God. Out of the ſame mouth proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bleſſing and curſing.</hi> And ſo this Libeller might by chance at the laſt ſpeak well of the King, though he had all along ſpoken evil, and that moſt maliciouſly, of ſome that are his moſt faithful Subjects.</p>
            <p>And to thoſe faithful Subjects doe I now for a concluſion of all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs my ſelf, humbly beſeeching, &amp; earneſtly intreating both you my moſt honoured Patron, and the reſt of thoſe Gentlemen, that were ſo mercifully &amp; miraculouſly preſerved, to ſpend your preſerved lives the more piouſly and religiouſly in Gods ſervice, becauſe they were ſo precious in his ſight, as to work ſo wonderfully and graciouſly in the preſervation of them, when they were ſo near unto deſtruction. It is the Lord that <hi>giveth life unto all, Act.</hi> 17.25. And it is the ſame Lord that hath <hi>redeemed your lives from deſtruction, and crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with loving kindneſſe and tender mercies, Pſal.</hi> 103.4. And therefore what can each of you ſay leſſe, then that which that Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt there ſaith, in contemplation of thoſe mercies, <hi>ver.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my ſoul: and all that is within me,</hi> bleſſe <hi>his holy Name. Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoul: and forget not all his benefits.</hi> And what can ye doe leſſe, to ſhew that you forget them not, then that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining courſe of your preſerved lives be anſwerable in ſome good meaſure to the mercies and miracles of their preſervation. And to mind you the more of Gods mercies and your duties, let me beg of you, what I hope you are already reſolved on before I mention it to you; That you would not fail to obſerve the laſt day of <hi>July,</hi> as a ſolemn day of Thanksgiving unto the Lord all your lives through; it being a day, wherein God (as <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid when he was delivered from the Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone &amp; Fire of <hi>Sodome, Gen.</hi> 19.) did <hi>magnifie his mercie which he ſhewed you in ſaving your lives;</hi> and that too, from the unſpeakable violence, and irreſiſtible force of the moſt dreadful inſtruments of his wrath and fury, his <hi>right-aiming Thunderbolts, that from the clouds, as from a well-drawn bow, flie to the mark,</hi> as they are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly deſcribed, <hi>Wiſdome</hi> 5.21. as alſo from thoſe mixt ſulphuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, fuliginous, conglutinous, fiery vapours, that they were, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly are wrapt up in; and which are Gods <hi>Arrows</hi> as well as the <hi>Thunderbolts,</hi> Pſal. 77. v. 17. Here both Philoſophie and Hiſtory would furniſh me with a very large diſcourſe of the nature and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Thunder; But <hi>Job</hi>'s Queſtion takes me off from medling
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57406:8"/>
much with the nature of Thunder, by ſaying, <hi>The Thunder of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power who can underſtand?</hi> Job. 26.14. Let it therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you, that it is <hi>the Thunder of his power;</hi> and remember, as oft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you hear it, or ought ſpoken of it, that on the laſt of <hi>July</hi> 1661. God himſelf, by his own power, and of his own free mercy, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed you from that otherwiſe mercileſſe power of his Thunder, that paſſeth all mans underſtanding; and that will help you the better to underſtand the loving kindneſſe of the Lord in your deliverance, and provoke you to be the more thankfull to him for it. And for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Thunder, you have ſeen and felt ſo much, that I preſume, you need not to be informed of any more, for the inciting you to that duty, which I am now minding you of. I ſhall therefore as to this particular, referre you onely to what holy <hi>David</hi> hath left recorded concerning the effects of Thunder, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 18. and 29. where Thunder is called <hi>the voyce of the Lord,</hi> and that voyce is ſaid to be power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or (as others read the places) mighty in operation. And ſome of thoſe mighty effects are there named, and the leſſon recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all men from the conſideration thereof, is the ſame that I am now recommending to you. Namely, Therefore to <hi>give unto the Lord glory and ſtrength:</hi> yea, <hi>to give unto the Lord the glory due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Name,</hi> and to <hi>worſhip him in the beauty of holineſſe,</hi> or, as it is in the margin, <hi>in his glorious Sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next and laſt place, When you are praiſing God for his delivering you from the power of his terrible Thunder, forget not to give him thanks alſo, for his delivering you in his due time, from the power of a malicious and ſlanderous hypocritical tongue; which, as it does in many reſpects reſemble Thunder, <hi>viz.</hi> in its irreſiſtible ſmiting, indiſcernable piercing, and viſible beſooting of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons it lights on, according as they are tempered or diſpoſed, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the nimble flying, and ſudden and unwarned hitting, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and killing, and the like: So it doth in divers reſpects tranſcend it: For Thunder falls moſt upon Beaſts, and Trees, and Buildings, &amp; ſeldome upon Men, as <hi>Pliny</hi> &amp; <hi>Scaliger</hi> have obſerved, &amp; our own experience witneſſeth: But an evil tongue falls wholly upon Men, and often upon the beſt of Men. Again, Thunder, when it does light upon Men, it ſpares often times their lives, and when it does kill, it kills onely their bodies; but the lying malicious hypocriticall tongue, ſpares nothing that it can hurt, and ſtrikes both bodies and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57406:9"/>
ſouls, and endeavours often times to take away mens goods alſo, and what is more precious, their good Names as well as their lives. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides (as the ſame <hi>Scaliger</hi> and <hi>Caſaubon</hi> have from others, that are far more ancient, tell us) when Thunder have ſlain any man, All men did generally carry ſome ſacred, though ſuperſtitious kind of Reverence to ſuch a body, and would neither bury, nor burn it, nor take it from the place where it was ſmitten, but there intomb it, and thought the very place ſacred, and accounted the body ſo ſmitten to be void of corruption. But the lying, malicious, ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tongue, ſo ſmites and kills, as that it reſts not there, but labours to render thoſe, whom it ſo deals with, moſt odious and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all men: and then it purſues them to their graves, and will not ſuffer them to remain quiet there, but ſpits its poyſon into their very aſhes. And therefore, if when any ſuch tongue hath ſmitten any of you, whom God himſelf hath ſpared, or ſhall further <hi>perſecute thoſe whom God hath ſmitten, and talk to the grief of thoſe whom he hath wounded</hi> (which is a true mark of a mercileſſe wicked man, Pſal. 69. v. 26.) God ſhall then pleaſe, by any unworthy Servant of his to vindicate your Honours and Credit. Let the Son of <hi>Syrach's</hi> Euchariſticall expreſſions upon a very ſuitable occaſion, <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> 51. <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. be each of yours, and ſay with him, <hi>I will thank thee O Lord and King, and praiſe thee, O God my Saviour, I do give praiſe unto thy Name. For thou art my defender and helper, and haſt preſerved my body from deſtruction, and from the ſnare of a ſlanderous tongue, and from the lips that forge lies, and hast been mine helper againſt mine adverſaries, And haſt delivered me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy mercies, and greatneſſe of thy Name, from the teeth of them that were ready to devour me, and out of the hands of ſuch that ſought after my life, and from the manifold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions which I had, and from the choaking of fire on every ſide, and from the depth of the belly of hell, and from an unclean tongue, and from lying words.</hi> And this will be amongſt many other comforts to yourſelves, an ample reward to him that hath adventured the cenſure of malicious evil tongues, to vindicate you from the malice and evil of the tongue.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57406:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
